{"tossups":[{"question":"Daniel Koshland defined this word in terms of seven pillars represented by the acronym PICERAS. A 1944 book that attempts to define this word theorizes that “aperiodic crystals” are crucial to this concept. A committee assembled by NASA in 1994 came up with a ten-word sentence as a working definition of this word. An Erwin Schrödinger book titled (*) “What Is [this word]?” argues that this property is possessed by systems that maintain negative entropy. The pseudoscientific idea that non-mechanistic forces are essential to this concept is known as vitalism. Viruses are sometimes described as being at the “edge” of this concept. For 10 points, name this biological concept whose hallmarks include homeostasis, evolution, and reproduction.","formatted_answer":"<b><u>life<\/b><\/u> [accept <b><u>alive<\/b><\/u>; accept <b><u>living<\/b><\/u>]","answer":"<b><u>life<\/b><\/u> [accept <b><u>alive<\/b><\/u>; accept <b><u>living<\/b><\/u>]","category":"Science","subcategory":"Chemistry","packetNumber":9,"questionNumber":1},{"question":"A modernized vocabulary for this language was promoted in the 1888 book My Journey by a linguist who worked in France. An orthography for this language using only two diacritics instead of five was mandated by a socialist government that took power in a landslide 1981 victory over the New Democracy Party. A lexically conservative form of this language was promoted by a military (*) junta [HUNT-uh] that employed the ESA secret police and ruled from 1967 to 1974, known as the Regime of the Colonels. This language’s namesake “question” was a long-running dispute between supporters of its Katharevousa [kah-thuh-REH-voo-sah] and demotic forms. For 10 points, name this language spoken by Andreas Papandreou [ahn-DRAY-ahss pah-pahn-DRAY-oo].","formatted_answer":"modern <b><u>Greek<\/b><\/u> language [or <b><u>Elliniká<\/b><\/u>]","answer":"modern <b><u>Greek<\/b><\/u> language [or <b><u>Elliniká<\/b><\/u>]","category":"Philosophy","subcategory":"Philosophy","packetNumber":9,"questionNumber":2},{"question":"After a horse taps out a poem whose first letters spell out this French word, Orpheus is declared a fraud in Jean Cocteau’s play Orpheus. This word is also the name of an extremely uncouth character played by Denis Lavant [duh-NEE luh-VAHN] in a 2009 Leos Carax [lay-oss kah-ROCKS] short and reprised in Holy Motors. This word is the French equivalent of the Italian in (*) bocca al lupo [een BOHK-kah all LOO-poh] or the English “break a leg.” An “r” is added to this word in the neologism that opens Alfred Jarry’s Ubu Roi [oo-boo RWAH]. This word is sometimes called “the word of Cambronne” [kahm-BROHN] in reference to Pierre Cambronne’s supposed response when he was asked to surrender at Waterloo. It’s not zut [zoot], but this word is followed by the word alors [ah-LOR] in a mild oath. For 10 points, name this French word for “shit.”","formatted_answer":"<b><u>merde<\/b><\/u> [accept <b><u>merde<\/b><\/u> alors]","answer":"<b><u>merde<\/b><\/u> [accept <b><u>merde<\/b><\/u> alors]","category":"History","subcategory":"World History","packetNumber":9,"questionNumber":3},{"question":"Leonard Bernstein conducts a work by this composer after lecturing about humor in music on the album that won the 1962 Grammy for Best Spoken Word Album. Appropriately, the last word sung in this composer’s last work is “death,” which introduces a theme that this composer had used sixty years earlier. Critics often refer to this composer’s late works, including the Oboe Concerto and the Horn Concerto No. 2, using the phrase (*) “Indian summer.” This composer’s last opera, which deals with the question of whether words or music is the greater art, is called Capriccio. In an opera by this composer with a libretto by Hugo von Hofmannsthal [HOO-goh fon HOHF-mahn-stall], Italian words are clumsily deployed by Baron Ochs. For 10 points, name this composer of Der Rosenkavalier [dair ROH-zin-kah-vah-leer] and Also sprach Zarathustra [ALL-zoh shprock tsah-rah-TOOST-rah].","formatted_answer":"Richard (Georg) <b><u>Strauss<\/b><\/u>","answer":"Richard (Georg) <b><u>Strauss<\/b><\/u>","category":"Fine Arts","subcategory":"Auditory Fine Arts","packetNumber":9,"questionNumber":4},{"question":"In a work by this person, a linguist accidentally summons a bear by hypothesizing that the original English word for bear might have been “arth.” Another work by this person is about a 1-year-old who mostly speaks Proto-Indo-European but is well on his way to acquiring Old English. This person coined the word “malamanteau” [MAL-uh-mon-TOH] to make fun of (*) Wikipedia’s writing style, prompting a lengthy argument about whether to add a redirect. This coiner of the term “nerd sniping” explained complex topics using only the thousand most common English words in his book Thing Explainer. The title of his best-known creation was chosen as a four-letter string with no phonetic pronunciation. For 10 points, name this creator of the webcomic xkcd.","formatted_answer":"Randall (Patrick) <b><u>Munroe<\/b><\/u>","answer":"Randall (Patrick) <b><u>Munroe<\/b><\/u>","category":"Trash","subcategory":"Trash","packetNumber":9,"questionNumber":5},{"question":"The interpretation of this word, as used in the name of an 1857 law also called Lord Campbell’s Act, was considered in the English case Regina v. Hicklin. John Marshall Harlan II disputed the idea that this word is as easy to define as “poison ivy” in his dissent in a case that was combined with Alberts v. California. The average person’s application of “contemporary (*) community standards” is one of the three prongs of the Miller test for whether this word is applicable. Though this word is not used in the concurrence in Jacobellis v. Ohio written by Potter Stewart, Stewart’s quote “I know it when I see it” is often taken as his definition of this term. For 10 points, name this word describing material that is offensive to standards of decency or morality.","formatted_answer":"<b><u>obscenity<\/b><\/u> [or <b><u>obscene<\/b><\/u>]","answer":"<b><u>obscenity<\/b><\/u> [or <b><u>obscene<\/b><\/u>]","category":"History","subcategory":"American History","packetNumber":9,"questionNumber":6},{"question":"A book that emphasizes the brutality of some of this author’s short poems is subtitled Words Chosen Out of Desire. R. P. Blackmur wrote that lines like “The moonlight fubbed the girandoles” give this poet a bad reputation among readers who dislike words with an “air of preciousness.” In a six-part poem that begins by declaring that “man is the (*) intelligence of his soil,” this poet used the word “exchequering” to exemplify the different sounds made by the letter C. This poet’s expansive vocabulary is exemplified by a line about “complacencies of the peignoir” in a poem about a woman staying home instead of going to church. For 10 points, name this poet who included “Sunday Morning” in his collection Harmonium.","formatted_answer":"Wallace <b><u>Stevens<\/b><\/u>","answer":"Wallace <b><u>Stevens<\/b><\/u>","category":"Literature","subcategory":"American Literature","packetNumber":9,"questionNumber":7},{"question":"This word, or a variant ending with a double letter, can mean either a pattern of threads and yarns in a Scottish tartan or the system of tunnels where a badger lives. This word can mean the distance that a saw tooth is bent away from the blade to prevent the blade from binding in the wood. “Run” recently overtook this word as the word with the most different meanings in the (*) OED. In Britain but not North America, this three-letter word commonly means to construct a crossword. This is the name of a game with 81 cards with unique combinations of shapes, shadings, colors, and numbers of shapes. In volleyball, it means to hit the ball such that your teammate can then spike it. For 10 points, name this word that can mean a group of reps in weight training or a group of games in tennis.","formatted_answer":"<b><u>set<\/b><\/u>","answer":"<b><u>set<\/b><\/u>","category":"Fine Arts","subcategory":"Auditory Fine Arts","packetNumber":9,"questionNumber":8},{"question":"This word symbolically precedes “threes” in the name of a backing band made up of Marcia Griffiths, Judy Mowatt, and the lead singer’s wife Rita. This word, when followed by the ending “-ance” or “-tesvar,” refers to a dialect that makes heavy use of this word, developed by members of a certain “house” in the 1950s. The beginnings of words like “continually” are replaced with this word in a dialect based on the principle of “word-sound-power.” Two occurrences of this word are linked by the word “and” in a phrase that refers to the (*) oneness of Jah. In the term for a diet that promotes “livity,” this pronoun is emphasized by removing the “v” from a standard English word. For 10 points, name this pronoun that is used by Rastafarians to emphasize individual subjectivity.","formatted_answer":"<b><u>I<\/b><\/u>","answer":"<b><u>I<\/b><\/u>","category":"Religion","subcategory":"Religion","packetNumber":9,"questionNumber":9},{"question":"In this language, sipapu refers to a hole in the floor representing the place where the first humans emerged from the earth. This language’s vocabulary is particularly well-equipped to describe “vibratile phenomena,” according to a linguist who posited that this language imposes forms called “manifested” and “manifesting” on the universe. This language’s tense system was contrasted with that of (*) “Standard Average European” by Benjamin Whorf, who claimed that this language has no words that refer directly to the concept of time. A phrase meaning “life out of balance” in this language provides the title of the 1982 film Koyaanisqatsi [koy-ah-nee-SKAHT-see]. For 10 points, name this language spoken by a Puebloan people in northeastern Arizona.","formatted_answer":"<b><u>Hopi<\/b><\/u> language [or <b><u>Hopilàvayi<\/b><\/u>]","answer":"<b><u>Hopi<\/b><\/u> language [or <b><u>Hopilàvayi<\/b><\/u>]","category":"Social Science","subcategory":"Social Science","packetNumber":9,"questionNumber":10},{"question":"One of these expressions based on a phrase meaning “the insane woman at mass” was used by François Rabelais [rob-LAY]. The comedy group Capitol Steps typically included a routine consisting of a litany of these expressions in each of their shows. The name of Tyler the Creator’s streetwear brand was created as this type of expression. The name of an annual music poll created by Robert (*) Christgau [KRIST-gow] for The Village Voice was created as one of these expressions based on the words “jazz” and “pop.” According to a popular folk etymology, the word “butterfly” originated as this type of expression. Classic examples of these phrases include “a well-boiled icicle” and “a shoving leopard.” For 10 points, a British reverend lends his name to what expressions in which the first sounds of two words are exchanged?","formatted_answer":"<b><u>spoonerism<\/b><\/u>s [accept <b><u>contrepèterie<\/b><\/u>s]","answer":"<b><u>spoonerism<\/b><\/u>s [accept <b><u>contrepèterie<\/b><\/u>s]","category":"Literature","subcategory":"American Literature","packetNumber":9,"questionNumber":11},{"question":"Jason W. Moore proposed adding this suffix to the word “capital” as an alternative to the “shallow historicization” of another word ending with this suffix. Donna Haraway’s book Staying with the Trouble adds this suffix to the word “Cthulhu” [kuh-THOO-loo]. A working group named for a word with this suffix aims to choose a “golden spike,” or Global Boundary Stratotype Section and Point, to formally define that word. That working group has proposed the (*) Trinity test as the starting point for a term ending with this suffix. This suffix comes from a Greek word for “new” and is combined with a Greek word for “whole” to refer to a time period that began in the 10th millennium BCE. For 10 points, what suffix is combined with the root “anthropo-” to describe the geological epoch impacted by human activity?","formatted_answer":"-o<b><u>cene<\/b><\/u> [accept Capitalo<b><u>cene<\/b><\/u>; accept Cthulhu<b><u>cene<\/b><\/u>; accept Anthropo<b><u>cene<\/b><\/u>; accept Holo<b><u>cene<\/b><\/u>]","answer":"-o<b><u>cene<\/b><\/u> [accept Capitalo<b><u>cene<\/b><\/u>; accept Cthulhu<b><u>cene<\/b><\/u>; accept Anthropo<b><u>cene<\/b><\/u>; accept Holo<b><u>cene<\/b><\/u>]","category":"Science","subcategory":"Other Science","packetNumber":9,"questionNumber":12},{"question":"This word likely derived from a word for a spoiled child or milksop, which in turn may have come from a word for a misshapen egg. A comical alphabet named either for “surrealist” or for this word includes entries like “O for the garden wall” and “Y for Gawd’s sake.” Although this word is etymologically unrelated to the similar name of a mythical land of (*) plenty, that name has been jocularly applied to the same city that this word refers to. Traditionally, this word referred to a person who was born within earshot of the Bow Bells. Stairs are referred to as “apples,” short for “apples and pairs,” in a rhyming slang named for this word. For 10 points, name this dialect of English spoken by many working-class Londoners.","formatted_answer":"<b><u>Cockney<\/b><\/u> [accept <b><u>Cockney<\/b><\/u> Alphabet; accept <b><u>Cockney<\/b><\/u> rhyming slang] (The mythical land of plenty is Cockaigne.)","answer":"<b><u>Cockney<\/b><\/u> [accept <b><u>Cockney<\/b><\/u> Alphabet; accept <b><u>Cockney<\/b><\/u> rhyming slang] (The mythical land of plenty is Cockaigne.)","category":"Literature","subcategory":"British Literature","packetNumber":9,"questionNumber":13},{"question":"A 1966 interview of this person is the first recorded use of the phrase “different strokes for different folks.” In a 1975 Playboy interview, this person said “These are words of wisdom, so pay attention, Mr. Playboy” while rattling off sayings like “Love is a net where hearts are caught like fish.” This person opposes “Mr. Tooth Decay” on a 1976 (*) spoken word album, and also released a 1963 spoken word album that is often described as a predecessor of rap music. This athlete shouted “Eat your words!” at journalists before boasting “I shook up the world” after a 1964 victory in Miami Beach. The word “rope-a-dope” was first used to describe this athlete’s defensive technique. For 10 points, name this boxer known as “The Greatest.”","formatted_answer":"Muhammad <b><u>Ali<\/b><\/u> [or Cassius Marcellus <b><u>Clay<\/b><\/u> Jr.]","answer":"Muhammad <b><u>Ali<\/b><\/u> [or Cassius Marcellus <b><u>Clay<\/b><\/u> Jr.]","category":"Fine Arts","subcategory":"Auditory Fine Arts","packetNumber":9,"questionNumber":14},{"question":"Ludwig Tieck argued that the defining characteristic of works described by this word was the presence of a Wendepunkt [VEN-duh-poonkt], or “turning point.” In a preface called “Go Little Book,” this word is called a “slack, boneless, affected word that we do not need to describe anything.” Katherine Anne Porter hated this word, which is used in the original-language title of Stefan Zweig’s The (*) Royal Game. Ian McEwan’s On Chesil Beach was controversially nominated for the Booker despite McEwan himself using this word to describe it. This word of Italian origin can refer to the stories that make up The Decameron, or to works like Breakfast at Tiffany’s and Billy Budd. For 10 points, name this word for a fictional narrative longer than a short story but shorter than a novel.","formatted_answer":"<b><u>novella<\/b><\/u> [or <b><u>novelle<\/b><\/u>; reject “novel”; reject “novelette”]","answer":"<b><u>novella<\/b><\/u> [or <b><u>novelle<\/b><\/u>; reject “novel”; reject “novelette”]","category":"Literature","subcategory":"British Literature","packetNumber":9,"questionNumber":15},{"question":"A claim about the meaninglessness of this word provides the title of a weekly podcast produced by the QI [Q-I] Elves. The Hebrew translation of this word is followed by the adjective gadol [gah-DOLE] in a book of the Bible that later mysteriously uses the feminine form of this word in the next chapter. The Greek translation of this word was used as an acronym for a phrase meaning (*) “Jesus Christ, Son of God, Savior.” In 2022, a California court ruled that the definition of this word includes bees for the purposes of a state conservation law. In some situations, the Catholic Church has included beavers in the definition of this word for people observing Lent. “G-H-O-T-I” is a whimsical respelling of, for 10 points, what word that historically referred to any aquatic animal?","formatted_answer":"<b><u>fish<\/b><\/u> [accept No Such Thing as a <b><u>Fish<\/b><\/u>] (The Book of Jonah refers to the fish that swallows Jonah as dag gadol, or “great fish,” but then uses the feminine dagah to refer to the fish from which Jonah prays, leading some rabbis to propose that God transferred Jonah to a different fish.)","answer":"<b><u>fish<\/b><\/u> [accept No Such Thing as a <b><u>Fish<\/b><\/u>] (The Book of Jonah refers to the fish that swallows Jonah as dag gadol, or “great fish,” but then uses the feminine dagah to refer to the fish from which Jonah prays, leading some rabbis to propose that God transferred Jonah to a different fish.)","category":"Religion","subcategory":"Religion","packetNumber":9,"questionNumber":16},{"question":"As a political statement, a Spanish word for “squatter” is spelled in this unusual manner. A 1965 album whose name is spelled in this unusual manner spawned the hit “Till the End of the World.” Another album whose name is spelled in this manner was inspired by the film Black Orpheus and includes the single “Afterlife.” According to a dubious theory, Japan promoted spelling another (*) country’s name in this manner so that “Japan” would appear earlier alphabetically. This affectation is used in the name of a video game series where “fatalities” are prompted by the announcer saying “finish him” or “finish her.” For 10 points, name this spelling affectation used twice in the name of the donut chain Krispy Kreme.","formatted_answer":"spelled with a <b><u>k<\/b><\/u> instead of a <b><u>c<\/b><\/u> [prompt on partial answers; prompt on “deliberately <u>misspelled<\/u>”] (In order, the clues refer to okupa, The Kink Kontroversy by the Kinks, Reflektor by Arcade Fire, Korea, and Mortal Kombat.)","answer":"spelled with a <b><u>k<\/b><\/u> instead of a <b><u>c<\/b><\/u> [prompt on partial answers; prompt on “deliberately misspelled”] (In order, the clues refer to okupa, The Kink Kontroversy by the Kinks, Reflektor by Arcade Fire, Korea, and Mortal Kombat.)","category":"Science","subcategory":"Math","packetNumber":9,"questionNumber":17},{"question":"In one book, this person recalls accidentally using the Latin words non vixit [nohn WEEK-seet] instead of non vivit [nohn WEE-weet] after seeing those words on the pedestal of a statue. This person used a complex chain of steps involving a journey to Herzegovina to explain the forgetting of Luca Signorelli’s last name. In a 1919 essay inspired by the work of Ernst (*) Jentsch, this thinker contrasted a word meaning “concealed” with a related word meaning “uncanny.” This person’s grandson Ernst uttered the sounds “ooh” and “aah,” which he interpreted as the words fort and da [dah], in a game recounted in this man’s essay Beyond the Pleasure Principle. For 10 points, name this psychologist who introduced the terms “id,” “ego,” and “superego.”","formatted_answer":"Sigmund <b><u>Freud<\/b><\/u> [or Sigismund Schlomo <b><u>Freud<\/b><\/u>]","answer":"Sigmund <b><u>Freud<\/b><\/u> [or Sigismund Schlomo <b><u>Freud<\/b><\/u>]","category":"Fine Arts","subcategory":"Visual Fine Arts","packetNumber":9,"questionNumber":18},{"question":"Many clemency petitions written in this manner were received during the trial following the assassination of the Japanese prime minister Inukai Tsuyoshi in the May 15 incident. The words “your life depends on lying close” are written in this manner in a scene from The Narrative of Arthur Gordon Pym of Nantucket. Annabella writes a letter to her brother Giovanni in this manner in (*) ‘Tis Pity She’s a Whore. A copy of the Qur’an commissioned for Saddam Hussein’s 60th birthday was supposedly written in this manner. The German word for “revenge,” Rache [ROCK-uh], is written on a wall in this manner in the Sherlock Holmes novel A Study in Scarlet. For 10 points, Draco’s constitution was said to be so harsh that it was written in what substance instead of ink?","formatted_answer":"written in <b><u>blood<\/b><\/u>","answer":"written in <b><u>blood<\/b><\/u>","category":"History","subcategory":"World History","packetNumber":9,"questionNumber":19},{"question":"Slang terms from this country include acere [ah-SAY-ray], meaning “dude,” and qué bolá [kay boh-LAH], meaning “what’s up.” This country’s double-humped tractor-trailer buses are nicknamed camellos [kah-MAY-zhohss] because of their resemblance to camels. A poet from this country is known for his use of rhythmic onomatopoeia like sóngoro cosongo [SOHN-goh-roh koh-SOHN-goh] and (*) mayombe-bombe [mah-YOHM-bay BOHM-bay]. This country’s version of rice and beans is called moros y cristianos [MOH-rohss ee crease-TYAH-nohss], meaning “Moors and Christians.” People who left this country on Freedom Flights were derogatorily called “worms,” or gusanos [goo-SAH-nohss], by a leader of this country. In a classic hyperforeignism, a tilde is added to the name of a hot pepper named for this country’s capital. For 10 points, the habanero [hah-bah-NAY-roh] pepper is named for what country’s capital?","formatted_answer":"Republic of <b><u>Cuba<\/b><\/u> [or República de <b><u>Cuba<\/b><\/u>]","answer":"Republic of <b><u>Cuba<\/b><\/u> [or República de <b><u>Cuba<\/b><\/u>]","category":"Geography","subcategory":"Geography","packetNumber":9,"questionNumber":20}],"bonuses":[]}
